<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Operation Code Blog</title>
    <description>Operation Code is on a mission to trailblaze a new career path opportunity for military veterans in software development and coding.
</description>
    <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://operationcode.org/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2016 11:19:41 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2016 11:19:41 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.3</generator>

      <item>
        <title>Meet CodeConf LA Attendee, Conrad Hollomon</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My name is Conrad Hollomon, born and raised in Virginia Beach VA. I’m a US Army officer, currently on reserve status, one tour in Afghanistan from 2010-2011. In the military, I led IT and tactical communications teams, and worked hard to develop my fellow Soldiers and help them reach their full potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m currently working for a venture-backed energy tech startup called SparkMeter, developing a smart metering system that’s being widely adopted by utilities serving customers in rural parts of Asia, sub-Saharan Africa, and Latin America and the Caribbean. It’s a great product that will help expand access to electricity for developing countries and emerging markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been fascinated by technology since I was a kid, and throughout the years, that’s never changed. I got started in the tech industry working in QA at a video game developer called Harmonix Music Systems, where I learned what it was like to develop innovative products, and how engineers and designers came together to deliver awesome experiences for people. Ever since, I’ve been dedicated to helping people build great products, working hard to be a positive driving force for any team, by bringing an creative, collaborative, and decisive mindset to the table. The experience has taught me that innovation originates from inspiring leadership, and that inspiring leadership originates from service to others. This takes integrity, authenticity, and just a little bit of audacity, too. Why CodeConfLA?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Github is a cornerstone of the open source community, and having the opportunity to be a direct part of that community via this scholarship is a great honor. The way we build and design software has such a tremendous impact on the end product that users see, and use, and love - finding ways to learn from each other, finding ways to build cool things better and faster, is a true joy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conrad Hollomon is a test engineer for SparkMeter, an Army Officer and an operations volunteer for Operation Code. He resides in Boston, Massachusetts and is &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hollomancer&quot;&gt;@hollomancer&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/06/27/meet-codeconf-la-conrad-holloman.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/06/27/meet-codeconf-la-conrad-holloman.html</guid>

        <category>News</category>


      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Google for Nonprofits</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Google is known for search. When we get stuck coding we Google every command line or inspect element error which leads to a blog, StackOverFlow, YouTube video, an article or a podcast that helps us get closer to the solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google is &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; known for helping nonprofits get more done through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/nonprofits/&quot;&gt;Google for Nonprofits&lt;/a&gt; program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to being enrolled in the program, we paid monthly to have a few email accounts for the team and this limited us in terms of growth and volunteer staff. That all just changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These past two weeks Operation Code has grown leaps and bounds organizationally, as we started issuing Operation Code email accounts to the software mentorship, scholarship, employer services, deploy and advocacy teams. Google for Nonprofits is enabling Operation Code to better coordinate, integrate and synchronize our services to better serve our military veterans coding community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From their web page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Google for Nonprofits offers organizations like yours free access to Google tools like Gmail, Google Calendar, Google Drive, Google Ad Grants, YouTube for Nonprofits and more. These tools can help you reach new donors and volunteers, work more efficiently, and tell your nonprofit’s story.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you so much, Google, for helping us in changing the world for those who’ve served our country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;David Molina is Founder and Executive Director of Operation Code, and an ex-Army Captain. He resides in Portland, Oregon.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/06/17/google-for-nonprofits.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/06/17/google-for-nonprofits.html</guid>

        <category>News</category>


      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Node Summit</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Along with teaching coding skills, Operation Code is also dedicated to setting up networks for our military veterans.  One of the best ways to grow a network is to attend a technical conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are delighted that &lt;a href=&quot;http://nodesummit.com/&quot;&gt;Node Summit&lt;/a&gt; - which will be held on July 26-28 in San Francisco, CA - has granted us four scholarship tickets for use by our veterans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From their web page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Node.js has taken its rightful place within critical enterprise environments and is well into “prime time”. Node Summit 2016 will bring together technology and business leaders and technology experts to discuss Node.js’ transformative role in the future of computing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you so much, Node Summit, for providing the means for our veterans to learn and grow.  We will see you there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nell Shamrell-Harrington is a volunteer and scholarship committee chair of Operation Code. She is the proud daughter of two Air Force officers. She resides in Seattle, WA.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/06/08/node-summit-sf.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/06/08/node-summit-sf.html</guid>

        <category>News</category>


      </item>

      <item>
        <title>TechSoup</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Operation Code Joins the TechSoup Community&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning to code is hard. This is further exacerbated by antiquated hardware and software. As a coding nonprofit serving the nation’s finest and their families, we’re always looking for new ways to partner and work with passionate businesses and organizations that care and help us meet our mission. Fortunately, there is TechSoup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TechSoup is a nonprofit with a clear focus: to make it as easy as possible for other nonprofits and libraries to obtain and use the technologies they need to achieve their missions. TechSoup provides access to over 400 technology products donated by more than 45 companies, including donor partners like Microsoft, Adobe, Cisco, Intuit, and Symantec. Read about their &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.techsoup.org/community/success-stories&quot;&gt;success stories&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are so very thrilled to join such as an amazing service and community of like-minded nonprofits who are building a more incredible and inclusive place to live and work. Special thanks to Sam over at &lt;a href=&quot;https://slack.com&quot;&gt;Slack&lt;/a&gt; who pointed us towards this wonderful organization, and the wonderful support team at TechSoup for getting us squared away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers and keep coding,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;David Molina is Founder and Executive Director at Operation Code, and an ex-Army Captain. He resides in Portland, Oregon.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/05/20/techsoup.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/05/20/techsoup.html</guid>

        <category>News</category>


      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Slack</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Operation Code 10k Slack Message Limit is History&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Software Mentor Protégé Program leverages real-time messaging application, &lt;a href=&quot;https://slack.com&quot;&gt;Slack&lt;/a&gt;, to welcome transitioning military, guard &amp;amp; reserve soldiers, veterans and their families share code and get help hacking on their websites or web applications, quickly communicate between volunteers and the board, all in a decentralized, asynchronous platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier last year iOS/Android developer &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nanoxd&quot;&gt;Fernando Paredes&lt;/a&gt; setup Slack and seamlessly integrated it into our Ruby on Rails application so that each time a new veteran joined, he/she would get an immediate invite and join us. But as you can imagine we quickly capped the 10k message limit prohibiting anyone to see past a few page scrolls. Last summer I sent over a request to Slack, but due to tax-exemption status couldn’t get it lifted. Fortunately, all that changed earlier this month with the IRS approving our tax-exemption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slack added fully searchable archive w/ unlimited messages, unlimited external integrations, simple usage statistics, custom message retention policies, guest access, and premium support to Operation Code’s Slack channel. As a result new channels are being created to better serve our military veterans community and their pursuit for becoming programmers. The latest channel: eloquent-javascript.&lt;br /&gt;
New military veterans who just joined Operation Code will now enjoy a more seamless experience and so will our &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OperationCode/operationcode/graphs/contributors&quot;&gt;contributors&lt;/a&gt; in adding new Slack external functionalities. Special thanks to the incredible team at Slack for always being helpful and for an incredible and ever useful tool that allows all of us who’ve served or are serving from all corners of the globe to learn to code and help the transition to become programmers less painful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers and keep coding,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;David Molina is Founder and Executive Director at Operation Code, and an ex-Army Captain. He resides in Portland, Oregon.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/05/20/slack.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/05/20/slack.html</guid>

        <category>News</category>


      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Benefits Creep, Part I</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Benefits-Creep Part I: Why Non-Profit Perks Go Up When They Shouldn’t&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the country was shocked this month to hear about the mismanagement of a large veterans’ non-profit organization.  Sadly, this was not shocking news to the veteran community, which had a long growing suspicion that this organization was spending too much money on lavish benefits for its leaders and staff.   Like many organizations, it had lost its way – getting caught up in its own success and giving the appearance that its leaders were more interested in serving themselves and not veterans.  In contrast to mission-creep, where an organization gets farther and farther from its core mission, this is “Benefits-Creep” in which an organization over-expands the perks it offers to leadership and staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most of us who found or start working for non-profits, we do so with the best intentions at heart.  With success, however, it becomes easier to justify expenses that in the beginning we never would have considered.  There are a few reasons for benefits-creep:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More money.  With more money, “luxury” expenses become easier to afford.  Also, if looked at as a percentage of the budget, expenses may even go down as the quality of things like hotels, dinners, and flights increase.  Clearly, many non-profit leaders are falling into the trap of setting expenses by a percentage of budget rather than by need.  Under a percentage allocation, if a travel budget of $1,000 can be justified on a $10,000 budget, then when the budget is $100,000, these leaders think is perfectly OK to spend $10,000.  While that may be true for business owners who get to reap the rewards of their increased profits, it is not true for non-profits who must also be looking to serve the public and must guard against percentage-based benefits-creep.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new normal.  Imagine a non-profit that is going through growing pains.  Maybe its management is having trouble dealing with expanded numbers of staff, or perhaps turnover has caused morale problems.  In order to fix these problems, which are having a real impact on the non-profit’s ability to provide services, leadership determines to have a “retreat” to refocus. Maybe they go to a leadership camp or fly-in the whole board for a team building weekend. While this is more expensive than their normal travel budgets, it may be entirely legitimate and help fix issues. The problem comes the following year:  there is no major issue but everyone remembers how nice last year’s event was.  Who wants to have a day long retreat in town, when last year’s weekend event by the lake was so much fun?  Once again, the travel budget goes up, and the following year it goes up again.  In this case, something that was meant to be an exception to policy became the new normal.  The new normal can cause benefits-creep almost anywhere in the budge from travel, dinners, snacks in the kitchen, to even who gets what type of office chair.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Outside influence and Expert Volunteers.  As a non-profit grows, more people are going to be interested in helping it. These may be business leaders that want to serve on the board or upper-income volunteers that want to help with events.  These volunteers are critical to an organization’s growth:  they help raise expectations, diversify funding streams, expose the organization to new management paradigms, and provide critical staff-power.  Operation Code is experiencing such an influx right now in its JAG Brigade, which has greatly increased its capability by adding lawyers who are volunteering from Hunton &amp;amp; Williams, one of the largest and best law firms in the country. Operation Code’s JAG Brigade is meant to do two things:  1. provide legal services to veterans in software development that have legal issues, such as incorporating their own business  or protecting intellectual property, and 2. assist coding schools with filing to be eligible to receive the G.I. Bill so veterans can use their benefits to learn to code.  Obviously, having top notch attorneys such as Penn Law graduate, Stefano D’Aniello, or Yale Law alum, Jordi Martinez-Cid, is critical to providing veterans the best legal support on these issues, but top law firms operate on radical different budgets than non-profits.  This budget gap may lead to different expectations.   The JAG Brigade is blessed – its volunteers from Hunton &amp;amp; Williams are down to earth attorneys and Hunton &amp;amp; Williams has a great deal of experience in helping small organizations and veterans.  Not every non-profit will be so lucky in getting expert volunteers with realistic expectations.  Leadership must help manage the expectations of successful leaders and experts brought in to help the organization.  Too often wealthy benefactors may suggest either budget busting endeavors or the expansion of small non-essential items that lead to inappropriate benefits-creep.  This is especially important to watch for as often these benefactors will offer to fund the extra benefits, and so it will seem to the non-profit that there is no harm.  However, perception can quickly become reality and explaining to other donors or the IRS how the retreat to a luxury resort was ear-marked by a donor that picked up the extra cost is not a good position to be in.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the source of benefits-creep, it can be dangerous to an organization’s bottom-line, its perception in the community, and worst of all to its legal standing.  Non-profit leaders must continually be managing both budgets and expectations to stop benefits-creep.  In Part II of this series, I walk through the strategies Operation Code has put in place to stop benefits-creep and ensure that when budgets go up our beneficiaries are the ones that benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are three reasons non-profits succumb to benefits-creep.  Please share your experiences with how you have seen benefits-creep impact non-profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark Kerr is Chairman of the Operation Code Board of Directors, Development Advisor to U.S. Southern Command, and an Iraq &amp;amp; Afghanistan war Army veteran. He resides in Miami Beach, Florida.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/05/14/benefits-creep-part-1.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/05/14/benefits-creep-part-1.html</guid>

        <category>News</category>


      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Beating the odds</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Beating the odds&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congrats! You just completed your boot camp! You spent the last 12/16 weeks of your life busting your behind and you came out victorious. You can make cool applications, you can configure a webserver, and you even understand how miserable/important it is to write unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the boot camp you just completed isn’t operated by Uncle Sam. There is no guaranteed position waiting for you after family day. You still need to convince someone other than your Mom that you and your skills are worth taking a chance on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is true. The tech field is growing. The need for developers appears to be growing each year. Learning to code is becoming very popular and it has never been easier/cheaper to get started. The vast amount of online resources available is mind-blowing. Boot camps are becoming more popular, and alternatives like FreeCodeCamp (sidenote - FCC has a pretty awesome curriculum and a great community) are keeping the dream alive. Oh and don’t forget about the constant stream of new Computer Science grads hitting the streets. What does this mean for people like you and me? It means that there are more people competing for those entry-level positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that you are Awesome. You were an amazing Soldier/Marine/Airman/Sailor and you will become an amazing developer. It just takes some time and a little elbow grease… You’ve dealt with deployments, long training exercises, endless 24 hour shifts, and soul-robbing safety briefings. You can land that first job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look some tips that I found helpful during my recent search. The suggestions are in no particular order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclosure - These suggestions may or may not apply to you and your situation/location. Please read them all but cherry-pick only what you feel is best for you and your bottom line. I am certainly no expert and currently in month two of my first developer gig. The market for developer gigs is highly dependent on location. A fresh boot camp grad located in Boise will likely have a different set of challenges than a grad located in the Bay Area. My experience took place in a mid-sized city on the West Coast with a relatively large number of boot camp grads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Portfolio page &amp;gt; GitHub page
Having an organized GitHub account with a solid commit history is absolutely essential. You must show employers that those cool acronyms you put on your resume are actually backed up by real work. However, looking at code on GitHub is boring. Often times your resume will be screened by HR and may get weeded out before it ever gets in the hands of a real human developer. A well designed portfolio site can help increase your chances. Your portfolio site should be clean and easy to navigate. Avoid free domains and get a real “.com” domain. “FirstnameLastname.com” or something similar looks way better than, “firstnamelastname.myfreewebhostingdomain.net”
Display all of your projects that you are proud of. Don’t just include a screen capture. Configure your applications so that the user can run them from your site. Include some brief comments for each application that highlight the technologies/ skills you used to create the application. “Card game built with JQuery, uses AJAX calls to pull user data from back-end, etc…” Include a link to the GitHub repo that houses the code for the particular application. Plaster your new URL on all of your resumes/job postings/LinkedIn. Check your site regularly to make sure everything is functioning properly!
You can register a domain name for a year for $10ish dollars and use a service like AWS for free hosting.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Network!
Trying to find a job sucks. Go hang out and commiserate with others in your same situation. Even small cities have all sorts of weekly/monthly tech meetups. These meetups serve multiple purposes, Meet up with others in your same situation. Trade notes on who is hiring, interview tips, and contact information for hiring managers. You may be a Ruby cat and your buddy may be a C# nerd. Look out for one another and send job postings his/her way when you see something that fits their talents. Learn! Meetups are great for getting out of “code bubbles.” In a boot camp setting, all of the students will tend to do things in a similar fashion based on what the instructor does or doesn’t do. Bust out of these routines and check out how others from different backgrounds tackle the same problems. Meet people that are actually doing what you want to do. Pretty self-explanatory… Ask them questions until you are blue in the face.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Craigslist?
When I first began my job search, I had numerous people tell me to avoid finding jobs on Craigslist. They told me that it was full of scams and flaky people. They were partially right. Craigslist does seem to attract all sorts of crap but it can also be a gold mine! Make sure you are still hitting up the big boards (indeed, glassdoor, dice, etc…) but also check out Craigslist daily. The scam postings are pretty easy to recognize and you can protect yourself by doing a little research on the company before you send in your information.
The Craigslist job section seems to attract smaller companies with less bureaucratic human resource departments. Therefore, if you get your application in ASAP (First 24-48 hours after it was posted) there is a very good chance that your resume will be viewed by a real live person instead of a resume-eating algorithm. (Sidenote- You should be responding to all job postings shortly after they are posted. I never had luck with postings that were more than a couple weeks old)
Craigslist postings also tend to require just a resume and cover letter. Anyone that has had to slay the Taleo dragon will understand how important this is.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Go big or go home!
You now have an awesome portfolio site, your resume is legit, and you tailor cover letters to the job posting. Start pumping out those applications. Get your numbers up! The more applications you put out there, the greater chance you have of getting a call back. Unless you already have a job you need to treat your job hunt like it’s a full-time position. Apply to all positions you feel qualified for. Be advised that many postings are written by non-technical people and are simply a wish list for the “perfect” candidate. Be honest on your resume and in your interactions with the company but don’t be afraid to apply for a position that requires “3-5 years experience” when you have 1-2 years experience.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Branch out
Maybe your boot camp focused on Ruby/JS/HTML. Perhaps it was Python/Django/JS. Or maybe PHP/JS/HTML? You are probably looking for the junior “web developer” position but don’t forget about the wide world of IT, QA, and mid level technical support positions! Check out indeed for QA and “technical support engineer” positions. Many of these positions will have you working with code on a daily basis and offer great opportunities for growth. Spending a year or two doing QA can be an awesome way to get your foot into the developer side of the house.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Intern
If you can afford to spend a couple more months without an income, look into internships. I have a met a number of people that rocked out during an internship and were offered a position with the company. Even if the company decides to not offer you a position, you will still be able to list this real world experience on your resume. If the company you are interested in doesn’t have an internship program, ask them if they would like a free intern for 6-8 weeks. Follow up job denial e-mails with a “thanks for considering me, perhaps you wouldn’t mind having me as an intern?” letter. Some internships will be reserved for students currently enrolled in a computer science/software engineering program but there is no harm in asking.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do not stop programming
Yes, boot camp is over. Yes, you are stressed out because of the job hunt. No, you can not stop coding. I don’t know about you, but after a few days away from the keyboard I start feeling a little foggy. Stay sharp and create more projects for the portfolio site.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do the standard stuff
Don’t forget about all the easy stuff that the Military taught you. Right place, right time, right uniform.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good Luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Charles Webster is a junior PHP developer and an open source fan. He is an Army veteran and currently resides in Portland, Oregon.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/05/14/beating-the-odds.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/05/14/beating-the-odds.html</guid>

        <category>News</category>


      </item>

      <item>
        <title>CodeConf LA</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At Operation Code, we go beyond just saying “support our veterans, troops, and their families,” we execute on it by providing the operating environment to become software developers. One company that is always shipping and enables Operation Code to fulfill our mission of getting more military veterans and their families coding is GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might remember last month, GitHub provided the Operation Code community scholarship tickets for &lt;a href=&quot;http://git-merge.com/&quot;&gt;GitMerge&lt;/a&gt; in New York and again have graciously extended the offer in supporting our military veterans transition to software development with next month’s CodeConf in sunny Los Angeles. From their &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/blog/2121-codeconf-la-tickets-are-now-on-sale&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“CodeConf LA will converge June 27-29, 2016 in sunny Los Angeles for three days of unforgettable discussions. This year’s event will focus on systems engineering projects, practices, and programs in the open source community. We’ll explore topics ranging from systems programming practices to operating applications at scale over three days and 30+ sessions, lightning talks, and workshops.””&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our Scholarship Chair, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nellshamrell&quot;&gt;@nellshamrell&lt;/a&gt; put it, “One of the best ways to learn, network, and find job opportunities in the IT industry is through attending conferences.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Marine veteran &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jjamespdx&quot;&gt;@jjamespdx&lt;/a&gt; put it, “For some veterans learning to code, the idea of going to a technical conference is a daunting task. You don’t know the jargon that well, you don’t know all the big names or faces, and you often times don’t know anyone else at the event. It’s a veritable mix of excitement to start getting into the community and the fear that you won’t or don’t belong. That’s exactly how I felt when the opportunity came up to go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/04/26/ruby-on-ales-2016.html&quot;&gt;Ruby on Ales&lt;/a&gt; via an Operation Code scholarship. Luckily for me, the experience was far greater than I could have expected.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there you go. Short suspense. &lt;a href=&quot;https://operation-code.slack.com/messages/@nellshamrell/&quot;&gt;Apply ASAP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current status: 1 ticket remaining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers and keep coding,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;David Molina is Founder and Executive Director at Operation Code, and an ex-Army Captain. He resides in Portland, Oregon.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/05/10/codeconf-la.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/05/10/codeconf-la.html</guid>

        <category>News</category>


      </item>

      <item>
        <title>501(c)(3) Confirmed</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At 1236 PST today, we received a much anticipated and welcomed phone call from the IRS regarding our submitted 501(c)(3) application. After some straggling to determine where the fax could be sent in, I took down the information from the agent and called our banker, Mr. Stanley Carpenter at &lt;a href=&quot;http://beneficialstatebank.com&quot;&gt;Beneficial State Bank&lt;/a&gt; with the request for fax support. At 1419, the official 501(c)(3) was in our inbox. What does this mean and how did we get here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it means Operation Code is an official public charity and retro active to last year June 2015. It also means our governing board of directors, and all of us volunteer staff have key ammunition to fulfill our mission and promise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the fall of 2014, I asked a friend and advisor, Mr. Jay Bloom, a former Executive Director of the Morrison Child &amp;amp; Family Center, former interim/CEO of United Way of the Columbia-Willamette about this problem I was seeing raising funds. At the time Charles Sipe had penned, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.switchup.org/blog/why-veterans-will-make-excellent-programmers&quot;&gt;Why Veterans will make excellent programmers&lt;/a&gt;,” and he/myself and dozens of other veterans that were joining Operation Code wanted to know how we could raise funds to pay code school tuition, room and board, since the New GI Bill was most certainly going to take time. Lots of time and I was frustrated and losing hope. I met Jay for breakfast and he recommended three unique courses of action, and I settled on the first and least expensive: fiscal sponsor. So the search began and I was turned down or given the run around by many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By December 2014, Portland Code Fellows Campus Manager, Ms. Jordana Gustafson, had suggested a few friends and one who ran a nonprofit and might, big might, provide fiscal sponsorship to resolve this scholarship issue. For 6 straight months last year I was full-time growing Operation Code under a fiscal sponsor, and while we created through the amazing Teresa Mahoney, &lt;a href=&quot;https://operationcode.org/media&quot;&gt;media clip interviews&lt;/a&gt; of code school CEOs, and veterans, hosted a Campaign Launch Party, donations and grants simply didn’t add up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twilio.com/signal/2015&quot;&gt;Signal 2015&lt;/a&gt;, I tweeted out to do a meetup at 21st Amendment and I was joined by many, including Laura Gomez, Nick Frost, Pete Runyon and Elmer Thomas. When the question was raised, “Dave, how can we help &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; exponentially grow Operation Code?” My answer was simple: “I need funds to file 501(c)(3) and a board of directors.” Pete’s answer: “Done.” The following day Pete joined me walking around San Francisco, literally, to meet with tech startup CEOs, government officials and veteran leaders. After getting back into Portland, Pete wired money over and we filed as an Oregon nonprofit and setup a bank account. The next task: emails. I secured david@ and pete@.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the proceeding months, Operation Code would become members of the Nonprofit Association of Oregon, install SSL &amp;amp; Stripe to take donations online, form the board of directors, and identify attorney’s that could support IRS application preparation. Regrettably, we blew through several months trying to get pro bono assistance, before getting the help of Susan Martin, CPA, at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gorgecap.com&quot;&gt;Gorge Capital&lt;/a&gt;. She loved our mission and has an eye for attention-to-detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 8th, Pete wired over $850 to include with our IRS application and it mailed. Today, ~41 business days later Operation Code is an 501(c)(3) nonprofit organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Dave Parker of Code Fellows, Michael Kaiser-Nyman of Epicodus, Mark Grimes of NedSpace, Maggi Molina of VetStartups and Raf Jauregui of SRVD for their support of our mission. Very special thanks to Mrs. Grace Stratton and Mrs. Jocelyn Tyree of Sen. Ron Wyden’s office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most especially my better half, Edith, and three young daughters, Maya, Paloma &amp;amp; Citlali, for their emotional support and love. Our board of directors for their persistence, oversight, and due diligence. Thank you.
We hope you’ll join us today, tomorrow and well into the future in our commitment of &lt;a href=&quot;http://operationcode.org/donate&quot;&gt;supporting&lt;/a&gt; the programming aspirations of America’s finest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers and keep coding,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;David Molina is Founder and Executive Director at Operation Code, and an ex-Army Captain. He resides in Portland, Oregon.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/05/04/501c3-confirmed.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/05/04/501c3-confirmed.html</guid>

        <category>News</category>


      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Ruby On Ales 2016</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For some veterans learning to code, the idea of going to a technical conference is a daunting task.  You don’t know the jargon that well, you don’t know all the big names or faces, and you often times don’t know anyone else at the event.  It’s a veritable mix of excitement to start getting into the community and the fear that you won’t or don’t belong.  That’s exactly how I felt when the opportunity came up to go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://ruby.onales.com/&quot;&gt;Ruby on Ales&lt;/a&gt; via an Operation Code scholarship.  Luckily for me, the experience was far greater than I could have expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Held in Bend, Oregon (an amazing high desert town and outdoor playground) Ruby on Ales is a two-day, single-track conference.  For those new to the conference world, “single track” just means that there aren’t different talks going on at the same time on different topics.  The event was housed in the historic &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.towertheatre.org&quot;&gt;Tower Theatre&lt;/a&gt; in downtown Bend and provided a comfortable, spacious venue for the entire conference.  Ruby on Ales has been operating for 6 years and features a range of presentations from more technical topics like the overview of the Crystal programming language to more community building things like Andre Arko’s talk on diversity and inclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My apprehensions about the conference talks themselves were mainly centered around hoping I could understand the material, not wanting to look weird if I had to step out to use the head or get away from the crowd, and hoping the presentations themselves just wouldn’t be dry technical explanations.  None of those things were a problem whatsoever.  The material itself was all very well laid out by the presenters and in any case where things might have been difficult to understand they provided further resources or even offered to speak with folks one-on-one about it after the talk.  The talks themselves were around 35-45 minutes and in between talks there was a 15-20 minute break so I never had to leave mid-talk and the breaks gave ample time to “recharge”.  The best part for me, however, had to be that the talks were anything but dry, technical speeches. Yes there were some technical topics covered but they were always done with humor and a sense of approachability.  The non-technical talks regarding the community and software development in general were warm and showed a deep focus on the building culture of the Ruby community as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the talks and conference day events would have been enough to make this trip a success in my mind, the true benefit and joy I got out of the conference was from what happened AFTER the conference ended each day. The first night I was invited by a group of strangers who didn’t know me (or each other, as I came to find out) who were headed out to eat dinner.  We shared our backgrounds, where we worked, and what we had thought about the talks so far as if we were all friends and colleagues.  One of the developers was from Canada and it was his first Ruby on Ales experience too while another dinner goer was a co-founder of a very popular error reporting software, yet, it was just like hanging out with people I had known for some time.  We then went our separate ways until an after party at a local bar that night where we met back up and continued sharing stories and laughing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next night, after the closing remarks of the conference, everyone headed out but the community was still there.  I had been invited by the developers from Guestfolio, a company based out of Whistler, BC, to their rental house to eat some food and hang out.  While there I had a great conversation with another coding boot camp graduate from their team about how the curriculum and placement systems could be improved.  After an hour or two there I headed over to a local restaurant to meet up with another programmer and some people he knew for dinner.  Once again, a group of strangers who I would likely never have approached before on my own welcomed me with open arms and soon we were all laughing and exchanging contact information.  Young and old, junior and senior developers of all different backgrounds at the same table as equals and colleagues just having a good time.  This was not something I had ever experienced before in previous conferences in other fields, people usually just stick with their own groups or coworkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next morning I went to breakfast before starting the drive back to Portland and reflected on the previous two days.  I had gone in to the experience with a lot of anxiety and thinking to myself, “You just have to suck it up and get through it.  You might pick something up but you at least need to show up.”  But now I left with a sense of community and of camaraderie that I hadn’t expected to find outside of a group of friends, coworkers, or fellow Marines.  I now look forward to the meet-ups and Ruby events that come up locally with excitement and view them as a chance to reconnect rather than as a fear inducing necessity for trying to develop a career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ruby on Ales truly was the best conference experience I could have hoped for as a veteran and new developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jesse James is a Ruby on Rails developer for TripGrid, a travel planning software startup.  He is a Marine Corps veteran and currently resides in Portland, Oregon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/04/26/ruby-on-ales-2016.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/04/26/ruby-on-ales-2016.html</guid>

        <category>News</category>


      </item>

  </channel>
</rss>
