<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Operation Code Blog</title>
    <description>Operation Code is on a mission to trailblaze a new career path opportunity for military veterans in software development and coding.
</description>
    <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://operationcode.org/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2015 22:59:59 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2015 22:59:59 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why Operation Code</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This week we proudly launched our Operation Code blog where we’ll share thoughts, insights and lessons learned as we build a coding veterans service organization. While these &lt;a href=&quot;https://operationcode.org/mission&quot;&gt;two Operation Code videos&lt;/a&gt; best tell our story, let me explain here the “why” we exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our nation faces an unprecedented technical talent shortage. This shortage isn’t just in San Francisco. But everywhere. Our veterans also face the highest unemployment in the country. Suicide rate is one too many. Veterans homelessness rate is one too many. At Operation Code, we’re on a mission to help military, veterans and military families learn to code and help fill the nation’s technical talent shortage. At the end of the day: get employed in a career that is defining everything around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We fulfill this mission through four-parts: coding scholarships, software mentorship, employment services and advocacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you may know, the New GI Bill isn’t widely accepted and available at code schools and coding bootcamps across the country. Even though, in many cases, it’s the fastest way to get coding and get a job in the software industry. Through your &lt;a href=&quot;https://operationcode.org/donate&quot;&gt;generous donation&lt;/a&gt;, you can help us close the veterans unemployment gap, today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning to code is central to Operation Code’s mission. Our ranks include both officer and enlisted, from active-duty to national guard and reserve, from all branches of our services, including Army, Navy, Marine Corps, Coast Guard and Air Force. Our Software Mentor Protégé Program leverages the Slack platform for real-time communication, code reviews, 1-on-1 and peer mentorship, all in a safe learning environment. &lt;a href=&quot;https://operationcode.org/action&quot;&gt;Signing up is seamless&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our network gets larger and more established, we expect the on-boarding process, between an underemployed/unemployed veteran coder and a software company, time gap to shorten. Currently, it’s way too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensuring the New GI Bill is available across a greater share of coding bootcamps to all of us is key. Amazingly only one code school in the country accepts this form of payment: Skill Distillery. But the process is simple. It all starts with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nasaa-vetseducation.com/Contacts.aspx&quot;&gt;State Approving Agency&lt;/a&gt; and then wait the two-years until applying for VA accreditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you, or anyone you know, might be interested in getting involved, whether as a software mentor, employer, donor, or anything else, please reach out. To all our friends, family and &lt;a href=&quot;https://operationcode.org/contributors&quot;&gt;contributors&lt;/a&gt; thank you for your support! We look forward to keeping you posted as things progress here on our blog, on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitter.com/operation_code&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/operationcode.org&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers and keep coding,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;David Molina is Founder and Executive Director at Operation Code, and a former Army Captain. He resides in Portland, Oregon.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2015 14:05:58 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2015/07/31/why-operation-code.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2015/07/31/why-operation-code.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Operation Code 1st Post</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello World! We’re Operation Code. And we’re on a mission to trailblaze a new career path opportunity for military veterans in software development and coding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check back here for our latest updates.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2015 09:43:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2015/07/25/our-first-post.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2015/07/25/our-first-post.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
