<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Operation Code Blog</title>
    <description>Operation Code is on a mission to trailblaze a new career path opportunity for military veterans in software development and coding.
</description>
    <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://operationcode.org/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2016 18:14:08 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2016 18:14:08 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Upcoming Conference Scholarships!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the best ways to learn, network, and find job opportunities in the IT industry is through attending conferences.  My very first tech conference was Cascadia Ruby 2011 where I was amazed at the variety of talks (many covering technologies and techniques I was immediately able to apply in my work), the interesting conversations in the “hallway track”, and the joy of talking with others working with the same technologies I was learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five conferences have kindly offered scholarship opportunities for members of Operation Code.  These scholarships will provide a free ticket to attend the conference.  Unfortunately, we are not able to cover travel expenses at this time, but we will encourage scholarship recipients to team up in carpooling, housing, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ruby.onales.com/&quot;&gt;Ruby on Ales&lt;/a&gt; - March 31 &amp;amp; April 1, 2016 - Bend, OR&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://git-merge.com/&quot;&gt;Git Merge&lt;/a&gt; - April 5, 2016 - New York, NY&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://conferences.oreilly.com/oscon/open-source-us&quot;&gt;OSCON&lt;/a&gt; - May 16 - 19, 2016 - Austin, TX&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twilio.com/signal&quot;&gt;Signal&lt;/a&gt; - May 24 &amp;amp; 25, 2016 - San Francisco, CA: Take on the buy one, give one Giving Challenge for SIGNAL, visit &lt;a href=&quot;twilio.com/signal/registration&quot;&gt;twilio.com/signal/registration&lt;/a&gt; and use the code OPCODEB1G1. Better yet, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/ahoy-assets.twilio.com/Signal/2016/SIGNAL%202016%20-%20Justify%20Your%20Trip.pdf&quot;&gt;tell your boss&lt;/a&gt; to help you help others.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://conferences.oreilly.com/velocity&quot;&gt;Velocity&lt;/a&gt; - June 20 - 23, 2016 - Santa Clara&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To apply for scholarship to Ruby on Ales, Git Merge, and Signal please &lt;a href=&quot;https://operationcode.org/action&quot;&gt;join Operation Code&lt;/a&gt;.  This will invite you to the Operation Code slack channel.  DM the Operation Code Scholarship Chair @nellshamrell from Slack with your name, email, branch of service, and one sentence about why you would like to attend the conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To apply for a scholarship to OSCON or Velocity, please apply through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oreilly.com/conferences/diversity-application.csp&quot;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; for a Conference Diversity and Inclusion Scholarship.  Please feel free to DM @nellshamrell or @david in the Operation Code slack if you’d like assistance!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nell Shamrell-Harrington is a volunteer and scholarship committee chair of Operation Code.  She is the proud daughter of two Air Force officers.  She resides in Seattle, WA.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/03/02/conference-scholarships.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2016/03/02/conference-scholarships.html</guid>
        
        <category>News</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Linux Academy Supports U.S. Veterans</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When I began my career as a software developer I remember being mystified by the systems which made the applications I wrote available over the internet.  As I took my first tentative steps into the world of system administration, I found that resources for learning these skills were few and tended to assume knowledge I did not have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://linuxacademy.com&quot;&gt;Linux Academy&lt;/a&gt; has taken bold steps into providing accessible and excellent quality system administration instruction.  Along with the basics of Linux, Linux Academy also provides extensive depth on the latest technologies like Amazon Web Services and Docker.  They are an extremely valuable resource to both new developers and seasoned system administrators looking to level up their skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linux Academy was also gracious enough to provide us with a number of free 6 month subscriptions, which are already being used by our veterans to learn new skills and build upon the skills they have learned at coding bootcamps.  We thank Linux Academy for helping our veterans learn the Linux skills of today and lay the foundation for the Linux and system administration skills of tomorrow!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2015/11/17/linux-academy.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2015/11/17/linux-academy.html</guid>
        
        <category>News</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introducing the New Operation Code Board Chair</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Like any startup things happen fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past week the Operation Code volunteer board of directors held a call to elect a new board chair. Nick Frost who had been serving as chair since late September stepped aside and while he’ll continue to serve as a board director and volunteer on the PR/Marketing Committee we needed to elect a new chair, begin assigning board committees, and an annual board meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the summer on Thursday, August 6th I began an interesting conversation. This time though it wasn’t like the other 99% emails. It had nothing to do with a veteran looking for scholarships to start or finish code school, a code school requesting to be added to our coding boot camp list, or a pull request. While each of these is important, this correspondence was very different. Instead it went something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Hi Dave,
I’m in the system. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wanted to see if there was any process in place for helping code camps/schools do the GI Bill paperwork… I’m former JAG and thought I could reach out to a couple schools in Miami to see if they are interested in me helping them getting approved to accept the GI Bill. Wanted to get a feel for what that might involve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;v/r,
Mark Kerr*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a series of emails, I got to know Mark. My response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Hi Mark,
Your efforts here would be greatly appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All code schools/bootcamps need to be 1st licensed through their state SAA (http://www.nasaa-vetseducation.com/Contacts.aspx). Once that’s done they have to wait 2-years. But like Skill Distillery, if we can help navigate these schools through the VA process, we can perhaps shorten this time wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could you help with this? Maybe take the South east region, or just Florida?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V/r,
Dave*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark’s response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Dave,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, let me call Florida tomorrow. If it looks doable then I can reach out to the bootcamps in Miami to see if there is interest.  Is it OK if I reference that I’m volunteering for Operation Code?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the process isn’t too involved (I have 2 small children, so time is a premium), then I’ll get to work on the S.E. as a whole. Also, if you are interested, I may be able to get some legal bro bono work from some of the bigger firms in Miami, which may speed up the process greatly as we can throw some more bodies at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V/r,
Mark*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Hi Mark,
Absolutely. Put me down as reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More pro bono the better. The more hands on deck on this the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can almost call this the JAG Brigade?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V/r,
Dave*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark’s response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*I like it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tried Florida but got a machine so will keep at tomorrow if I don’t hear back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V/r,
Mark*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(side note: states are understaffed at the SAA level. Sometimes one per state. Yes, one person.) My response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Mark,
What do you need from us as a nonprofit to credit pro bono work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V/r,
Dave*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark’s response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*In Florida it is on the honor system so wouldn’t be a need to verify but firms may want to document the relationship to ensure there is no conflict of interest. As a gov attorney, I’m exempt from needing to do pro bono but will have certain limits on what representation I could provide (which I don’t think will be an issue for this type of work, especially as it doesn’t technically require a law license to help with the paperwork).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V/r,
Mark*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Any luck in Florida?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V/r,
Dave*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark’s response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Kind of… The POC for Miami emailed me that she is out of town and will call me tomorrow when she is back in the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[next day]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Call went well. The Miami POC for the state is Madeline Mendez (info below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I was able to make clear that I’m a veteran, volunteering for veterans’ organization, and that neither I nor Operation Code are running programs, the call went pretty well.  She was able to look up Skill Distillery in the VA database so agrees that we should be able to do this here. Next step will be for me to see if there is any interest from the local camps. She also agreed to participate in a call or meeting in case there are any questions or concerns the schools have. A bit of paperwork to fill out but the hard requirements seem to be being registered already with the State board and in operation at least 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the best way to go forward is for me to start reaching out to the camps, see if there is interest, and then before we start on the paperwork – have a discussion with Madeline to make sure that the interested schools are likely to qualify. If they are, then I can help with the paperwork (although most of it looks pretty straightforward and is stuff that someone internal will have to complete). Madeline will then review the paperwork, do a site visit and submit to the State for approval.  Let me know if you think that will work, and I’ll get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V/r,
Mark*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next 70-days, we begin discussing the evolving formation of the JAG Team, on-boarding volunteer attorneys to support code school licensing, and the creation of a “Licensing Toolkit for Code Schools” and by September 17th invited Mark to consider joining our board ranks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Mark,
Your help with the toolkit, Florida and recruiting military veterans is beyond helpful. It has provided us much needed momentum and shift our approach to more service-organization and help these code schools better serve the military and veterans community, and engage a sector of the military community we hadn’t considered–former JAGs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like you, I have a family and three young daughter (under 7), and busy trying to survive while building this plane and flying it. Drum roll… We have a spot open on our new board of directors (https://operationcode.org/board), and would like to extend an invitation to join us. Goal is to have 12 directors (including 4 officers) to even out work load–because we’re an open source nonprofit, we get a ton of help from the software and developer community. The position open now: Secretary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I’m recruiting 5 more board members to include, an attorney, CPA, former nonprofit exec, influencer/Pentagon, VC or strategist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, our board is comprised mostly of military veterans who either are software developers or work for software companies, companies such as Twilio, Mattermark, Message Systems, SendGrid and Shiftboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only difference between now in your volunteer work, and acceptance: you’d be on the governing board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know and will do an intro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V/r,
Dave*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past Thursday, we had a board call. Happy to announce Mark Kerr, a Yale law graduate, former Army JAG, and the lead on the JAG Team accepted his nomination and was elected chair of the Operation Code volunteer &lt;a href=&quot;https://operationcode.org/board&quot;&gt;board of directors&lt;/a&gt;. The minutes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Board Meeting Minutes
November 5, 2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Call to order
David Molina called to order the regular meeting of the Operation Code Board at 1515 PST on November 5, 2015 via teleconference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roll call
Mark Kerr conducted a roll call. The following persons were present: Pete Runyon, Mark Kerr, Laura Gómez, Aimee Knight, David Molina&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proxy votes given to Molina by Josh Carter and Elmer Thomas for Chair nomination and votes based on meeting agenda, which was distributed to full board on November 3, 2015 via email. For Chair position, Carter nominated Kerr and Thomas nominated Gómez.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approval of minutes from last meeting
N/A&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open issues
Nomination of Board Chair
Discussion:  Runyon proposed self-nominations for Chair be proposed first in order to determine who is most interested in the position.  Gómez stated she was happy to serve as vice-chair due to other commitments and thought Chair position should be held by a veteran.  Kerr stated he was willing and happy to take the position.  6 votes in favor of Kerr as Chair including proxy, motion carried.  Kerr accepted position of Chair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nomination to fill secretary position.  Call for volunteers for position. Molina nominated Runyon.  Concern about possibility of holding multiple positions on board addressed. 5 votes in favor of Runyon as Secretary, motion carried. Runyon accepted position of Secretary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annual Board Meeting.  Discussion on where and when to hold annual board meeting.  2 members are on East Coast, remainder spread along West Coast.  Molina &amp;amp; Kerr agreed to discuss options after meeting and distribute  proposals for time and venue to the board to establish a consensus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volunteers for Committee positions.  Thomas, per proxy, volunteered for PR/Marketing &amp;amp; Programs.  Gómez volunteered for Fundraising &amp;amp; PR/Marketing.  Gómez excused from meeting.  Runyon volunteered for Finance.  Knight volunteered for PR/Marketing and offered to serve as spokeswoman when possible at events. Knight excused from meeting.  Molina to email remaining board members Carter, Fernando Paredes, and Nick Frost to determine their interest.  Kerr proposed that depending on time and interest of members Board might also establish task forces to supplement the standing committees to deal with short term issues. Kerr proposed that it would also be possible to use non-board volunteers to fill out committees.  Molina proposed that volunteers could be onboarded using Slack on #volunteer channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New business
No new business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Board discussed coordination of routine administrative issues:
Kerr added to Google Docs; Runyon to send information to CPA; Molina to email board re: interest in committee assignments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adjournment
David Molina adjourned the meeting at 1555.
Minutes submitted by:  Molina/Kerr
Minutes approved by:  Runyon
—&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/miamimark&quot;&gt;Mark Kerr&lt;/a&gt;:
At the height of the Iraq &amp;amp; Afghanistan war, Mark Kerr joined the Army Judge Advocate General’s Corps (JAG) serving as Defense Counsel in Korea, Iraq, Kosovo &amp;amp; Afghanistan. Previously, he was Associate at Hogan &amp;amp; Hartson where he led legal work related to regulatory compliance, mergers &amp;amp; acquisitions, and construction contracts involving oil/gas, wind/hydroelectric energy, and manufacturing. A graduate of Yale Law School, Mr. Kerr currently serves as Development Advisor to U.S. Southern Command Combatant Commander, General John H. Kelly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome aboard Mark!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2015/11/08/introducing-the-new-operation-code-board-chair.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2015/11/08/introducing-the-new-operation-code-board-chair.html</guid>
        
        <category>News</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Announcing Operation Code Board Officers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, we’re proud to announce our officers on the Operation Code board of directors, and one new director who joined the board this week, and will serve as Secretary. Please join me in congratulating the officers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Board Chair - Nick Frost; Board Vice Chair - Laura Gómez; Board Secretary - Mark Kerr; and, Board Treasurer - Pete Runyon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Board of Directors: Josh Carter, Aimee Knight, Fernando Paredes, and Elmer Thomas. &lt;a href=&quot;https://operationcode.org/board&quot;&gt;Learn more&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2015/09/30/announcing-operation-code-board-officers.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2015/09/30/announcing-operation-code-board-officers.html</guid>
        
        <category>News</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why Operation Code</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This week we proudly launched our Operation Code blog where we’ll share thoughts, insights and lessons learned as we build a coding veterans service organization. While these &lt;a href=&quot;https://operationcode.org/mission&quot;&gt;two Operation Code videos&lt;/a&gt; best tell our story, let me explain here the “why” we exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our nation faces an unprecedented technical talent shortage. This shortage isn’t just in San Francisco. But everywhere. Our veterans also face the highest unemployment in the country. Suicide rate is one too many. Veterans homelessness rate is one too many. At Operation Code, we’re on a mission to help military, veterans and military families learn to code and help fill the nation’s technical talent shortage. At the end of the day: get employed in a career that is defining everything around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We fulfill this mission through four-parts: coding scholarships, software mentorship, employment services and advocacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you may know, the New GI Bill isn’t widely accepted and available at code schools and coding bootcamps across the country. Even though, in many cases, it’s the fastest way to get coding and get a job in the software industry. Through your &lt;a href=&quot;https://operationcode.org/donate&quot;&gt;generous donation&lt;/a&gt;, you can help us close the veterans unemployment gap, today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning to code is central to Operation Code’s mission. Our ranks include both officer and enlisted, from active-duty to national guard and reserve, from all branches of our services, including Army, Navy, Marine Corps, Coast Guard and Air Force. Our Software Mentor Protégé Program leverages the Slack platform for real-time communication, code reviews, 1-on-1 and peer mentorship, all in a safe learning environment. &lt;a href=&quot;https://operationcode.org/action&quot;&gt;Signing up is seamless&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our network gets larger and more established, we expect the on-boarding process, between an underemployed/unemployed veteran coder and a software company, time gap to shorten. Currently, it’s way too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensuring the New GI Bill is available across a greater share of coding bootcamps to all of us is key. Amazingly only one code school in the country accepts this form of payment: Skill Distillery. But the process is simple. It all starts with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nasaa-vetseducation.com/Contacts.aspx&quot;&gt;State Approving Agency&lt;/a&gt; and then wait the two-years until applying for VA accreditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you, or anyone you know, might be interested in getting involved, whether as a software mentor, employer, donor, or anything else, please reach out. To all our friends, family and &lt;a href=&quot;https://operationcode.org/contributors&quot;&gt;contributors&lt;/a&gt; thank you for your support! We look forward to keeping you posted as things progress here on our blog, on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitter.com/operation_code&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/operationcode.org&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers and keep coding,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;David Molina is Founder and Executive Director at Operation Code, and a former Army Captain. He resides in Portland, Oregon.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2015/07/31/why-operation-code.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2015/07/31/why-operation-code.html</guid>
        
        <category>News</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Operation Code 1st Post</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello World! We’re Operation Code. And we’re on a mission to trailblaze a new career path opportunity for military veterans in software development and coding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check back here for our latest updates.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://operationcode.org/blog/2015/07/25/our-first-post.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://operationcode.org/blog/2015/07/25/our-first-post.html</guid>
        
        <category>News</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
